<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mobile | The Disco Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://aglover.github.com/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aglover.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-15T10:08:21+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://aglover.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Glover]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hybrid inappropriateness]]></title>
    <link href="http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/04/14/hybrid-inappropriateness/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-14T11:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/04/14/hybrid-inappropriateness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/confused.png">The mobile development landscape is <a href="http://skytechgeek.com/2011/09/10-mobile-application-frameworks-for-easy-development/">bursting at the seams</a> with frameworks and tools that enable you to target <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/03/25/modeveast-2012-panel-discussion/">two primary mobile platforms</a>: iOS and <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/android/">Android</a>. And the mobile community has <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/12/02/comprehending-the-mobile-development-landscape/">classified these frameworks and tools</a> into three categories: native, hybrid, and web. Unfortunately, limiting the classification to three <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/05/crowd-think-often-lacks-clarity/">is inadequate</a> as the term hybrid is too generic.</p>

<p>Web apps are truly ubiquitous because they take advantage of the browser and are thus, cross platform. You, for the most part, can get away with <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/01/cost-and-the-great-mobile-app-debate/">maintaining one code base</a> that can be viewed on iOS, Android, and the other minor players. Yet, the key point of Web apps is that they are <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/25/modevtablet-2012-video-mobile-web-realities/"><em>web sites</em>, not mobile apps</a>.</p>

<p>As you begin to blur that mobile app/mobile website line, you'll <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/03/04/its-a-question-of-wow/">stumble over various issues</a> like performance or varying behaviors depending on the underlying device.  Worse, you'll find that <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/24/a-tale-of-three-browsers/">not all browsers are created equally</a> and thus, you'll need to <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/02/17/circumventing-mobile-ux-expectations/">compensate for various scenarios</a> or use assorted compensating tools like <a href="http://modernizr.com/">Modernizr</a>. Or, you'll find yourself throwing the web app into a container because you want mass distribution via an app store or because you want to take advantage of some native feature.</p>

<p>And at that point, in the eyes of many, you've built a hybrid mobile app. But that's not the whole story.</p>

<p>Hybrid frameworks aren't all created equal.  There are, in fact, two flavors of hybrid-ness: <em>hybrid-web</em> and <em>hybrid-native</em>. Both are extremely different; in fact, to showcase the difference, I need only compare the "featured" apps of two hybrid frameworks: <a href="http://phonegap.com/">PhoneGap</a> and <a href="http://www.madewithmarmalade.com/">Marmalade</a>.</p>

<p>PhoneGap is a great framework for building hybrid-web apps. You code in HTML and JavaScript and the resultant code is run inside of a web view managed by a native container.  You ostensibly write one code base and deploy to all the primary mobile platforms. Similar frameworks are: <a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/mobile-solutions/worklight/">IBM's Worklight</a> and <a href="http://www.icenium.com/">Icenium</a>. <a href="http://www.sencha.com/products/touch">Sencha Touch</a> falls into this realm as well when you employ their container technology.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/mine/phonegap_example.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.madewithmarmalade.com/">Marmalade</a> is a hybrid-native app platform; that is, you can code in an intermediary language like C++ that is ultimately compiled down into native code (i.e. Java for Android, Objective-C for iOS, etc). These apps are not characterized by a web view in any way. They are native, close to the bone as it gets apps. The benefit is that you only had to write <em>one code base</em>, the underlying tool took care of the dirty work in making it work similarly on iOS and Android, for example. Similar frameworks are: <a href="http://www.coronalabs.com/">Corona</a>, <a href="http://www.mosync.com/">MoSync</a>, and <a href="http://www.appcelerator.com/">Appcelerator</a> to name a few.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/mine/marmalate_example.png"></p>

<p>Now look closely at the <a href="http://phonegap.com/app/feature/">featured apps</a> of each <a href="http://www.madewithmarmalade.com/app-showcase">hybrid framework</a>. They're <a href="http://phonegap.com/blog/2011/11/07/phonegap-application-craft-pain-free-mobile-app-development/">distinctly</a> <a href="http://www.madewithmarmalade.com/marmaladesdk/application/cut-rope">different</a> aren't they?</p>

<p>PhoneGap and the rest of the hybrid-web frameworks are good at producing informational apps. These apps can look beautiful and certainly can have some compelling features like tight integration with social networks and geo-tracking, for example. But they're inadequate for games and still lack a rich user experience when compared to more native apps like Flipboard or AngryBirds.</p>

<p>Marmalade and the rest of the hybrid-native crowd shine when it comes to highly interactive apps like games; what's more, these frameworks can build an app that generates a wow. And therein lies the crucial aspect that's missed when the industry blindly assumes all hybrid options are similar. They couldn't be more incorrect -- thus, we need at least four categories (native, web, hybrid-native, and hybrid-web) and we need to eschew the lone term "hybrid" as it lacks clarification and therefore has no meaning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Painless Android swipe detection]]></title>
    <link href="http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/04/07/painless-android-swipe-detection/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-07T10:37:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/04/07/painless-android-swipe-detection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/mine/gesticulate.png">Why bother building navigation buttons in an Android app when you can easily capture finger swipes? But, if you've ever implemented gesture section in Android there's the drudgery of implementing listeners and you also need to do some elementary Cartesian math. Save yourself the boilerplate bother mathematics and use a <a href="https://github.com/aglover/gesticulate">library</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/aglover/gesticulate">Gesticulate</a> makes it painless to detect straightforward swiping motions like up, down, left, and right. It's a simple jar file you include in your Android <code>libs</code> directory. Throw Gesticulate's <code>SwipeDetector</code> inside an instance of Android's <code>SimpleOnGestureListener</code>, for example, and you're detecting swipes with ease!</p>

<p>Gesticulate is used in Savvy Words, a flash card vocabulary app found on <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.b50.savvywords">Google Play</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Beacon50-Savvy-Words/dp/B00C535D20/ref=sr_1_1?s=mobile-apps&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1365339189&amp;sr=1-1">Amazon's Appstore for Android</a>. See the <a href="https://github.com/aglover/gesticulate">Github project</a> for more details such as code examples for how to use Gesticulate, how to build it, and to see Gesticulate's tests. Swipe on, baby!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crowd think often lacks clarity]]></title>
    <link href="http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/04/05/crowd-think-often-lacks-clarity/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T21:04:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/04/05/crowd-think-often-lacks-clarity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/crowd.jpg">In case you missed it, <a href="http://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> has an <a href="http://www.infoq.com/research/cross-platform-mobile-tools">interesting analysis regarding hybrid mobile app development frameworks</a>. They are profiling 12 tools and soliciting community feedback so as to make a <a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/insights">ThoughtWorks-like technology radar</a>. If you participate in the voting you are entitled to see the voting distribution.</p>

<p>What's interesting (and not too surprising) about this analysis is that frameworks like <a href="http://phonegap.com/">PhoneGap</a> or <a href="http://jquerymobile.com/">jQuery Mobile</a> (and laughably <a href="http://jqtjs.com/">JQTouch</a>?) are leaning more towards <em>adoption ready</em> when compared to frameworks like <a href="http://www.madewithmarmalade.com/">Marmelade</a>, <a href="http://www.coronalabs.com/">Coronona</a> or <a href="http://www.mosync.com/">MoSync</a>. But this radar lacks some clarifying dimensions -- for example, if you want to produce a mobile website on a lot of different mobile platforms quickly, then PhoneGap is probably the way to go. But if you're looking to create a mobile app, then the choice to use PhoneGap must be treated with extreme caution.</p>

<p>You cannot create a <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/03/04/its-a-question-of-wow/">compelling user experience</a> that works across <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/01/cost-and-the-great-mobile-app-debate/">all platforms consistently</a> with this framework right now. And it isn't even the fault of PhoneGap entirely -- it's <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/02/17/circumventing-mobile-ux-expectations/">HTML5</a>. That's why going with something like JQTouch without viewing the big picture of what you are building is laughable.</p>

<p>Frameworks like Marmelade or Corona might be a bit more difficult to get started with (after all, you code in something other than HTML or JavaScript) but they can produce a native app that offers a compelling user experience capable of generating a wow. Remember, native-ness <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/24/a-tale-of-three-browsers/">trumps the browser</a> almost always unless your app is a series of screens that don't require the user to interact.</p>

<p>Accordingly, the study lacks some needed dimensions -- mainly, whether or not you are building a mobile app or mobile website. Don't fall into the hype trap and jump into PhoneGap development unless you are sure what you are building is a simple mobile website and your audience isn't expecting something like Flipboard or AngryBirds. Otherwise, you'll find yourself investigating either pure play native development or frameworks that ultimately produce a native app.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MoDevEast 2012 panel discussion]]></title>
    <link href="http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/03/25/modeveast-2012-panel-discussion/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T18:34:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/03/25/modeveast-2012-panel-discussion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall, I had the pleasure of moderating a panel discussion at <a href="http://modeveast.com/">MoDevEast</a> entitled "<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7P-wNuHPL0">What Developers Love and Hate about iOS, Android, Windows and HTML5</a>" with five super star mobile app developers.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/b7P-wNuHPL0 "></iframe></div></p>

<p></p>


<p>The panelists are a diverse set, which made the interaction a lot of fun as each had unique perspectives. Check out what my friends <a href="https://twitter.com/rmm5t">Ryan McGeary</a>, Steve Jernigan, Michael Shapard, <a href="https://twitter.com/andytrice">Andrew Trice</a>, and Chris Kamsler have to say!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The bull's eye on mobility: Mobile for the masses]]></title>
    <link href="http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/03/06/the-bulls-eye-on-mobility-mobile-for-the-masses/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-06T09:28:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aglover.github.com/blog/2013/03/06/the-bulls-eye-on-mobility-mobile-for-the-masses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/mine/mftm_1.jpg">Since joining <a href="http://www.app47.com/">App47</a>, I've been lazer focused on mobility; consquently, I'm pleased to announce that a new mobile development series has debuted on <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/">IBM developerWorks</a>! The inaugural article,  "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses1/">A gentle introduction to Android</a>", begins by exploring the mobile landscape and introduces how to get started with Android app development.</p>

<p>As the article summary states:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The mobile landscape is rich with promise, and Android is a viable and exciting platform for developers who seek a way in. This new series starts with an introduction to Android that is tailored specifically for Java developers just getting started with mobile. Learn about Android's three-layer versioning system (and find out why it matters), then set up your development environment and build your first Android app.</p><footer><strong>IBM DeveloperWorks</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses1/'>Mobile for the Masses: A Gentle Introduction to Android</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>So what are you waiting for? Check out "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses1/">Mobile for the masses: A gentle introduction to Android</a>" and learn the ins and outs of Android development! Stay tuned for more articles to come and don't forget to watch for <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/mobile/">mobile focused articles on this blog</a> as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
