<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mobile | The Disco Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-20T19:54:13-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://thediscoblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Glover]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The significance of HTML5]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/10/05/the-significance-of-html5/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-05T21:18:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/10/05/the-significance-of-html5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/no-flash.jpg"><a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/html5/">HTML5</a> is important for three reasons. And its importance starts with the end of browser plugins. That's right. With HTML5, rich media aspects that were formally handled by plugins (think Flash), are now built-in. That's why there are <a href="http://www.w3schools.com/html/html5_new_elements.asp">new media tags</a> like <code>&lt;audio&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;video&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>Think about it for a second -- when's the last time you visited a site on your tablet that asked you to install a plugin? Never.</p>

<p>That's also why some older plugin laden sites do not work on your mobile device. Remember the whole "<a href="http://www.apple.com/hotnews/thoughts-on-flash/">Steve Jobs no flash</a>" kerfuffle years ago? Yep, Mr. Jobs was adamant that the iPhone would support HTML5 and not fall into the plugin trap. Incidentally, Google and other major vendors have since followed suit. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML5">HTML5 has the support of all major browser vendors now</a> -- Apple, Google, Firefox, Opera, and yes, even Microsoft.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/mine/alotofdevices.jpg">HTML5 is important because now that <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/12/02/comprehending-the-mobile-development-landscape/">all major vendors support it</a> -- including those in the mobile space -- you get a universal experience across a wide spectrum of devices. While particular features of HTML5 might <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/24/a-tale-of-three-browsers/">vary by device platform</a>, there are enough common ground features to build a compelling web app that looks and feels similar across the gamut of devices.</p>

<p>And as HTML5 <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/05/crowd-think-often-lacks-clarity/">continues to evolve</a>, the differences between various implementations should narrow. Accordingly, with HTML5, you get device ubiquity. You get a chance to build something once and have it work across a wide spectrum of browsers.</p>

<p>What's more, while the mobile market is still dominated by Apple and Google, as other players, <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/09/8-percent-is-itty-bitty-but-it-matters/">like Microsoft</a>, begin to establish a beachhead, app developers will have to contend with more than two platforms. For a variety of apps, like those being built for the enterprise, the promise of HTML5's device ubiquity starts to become quite appealing -- after all, building an app once, as <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/14/hybrid-inappropriateness/">opposed to three or more times</a>, is less expensive.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/amazonappstore.jpg">Finally, HTML5 is important because <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/07/why-amazon-appstores-support-of-html5-matters/">Amazon recently announced support for HTML5</a> apps in their App Store for Android. Previous to this announcement, pure HTML5 apps had no real mass distribution model. HTML5 app developers relied on a search engine, while native app developers have a direct channel to consumers that cuts through a lot of noise and makes it easy to find specific apps.</p>

<p>Consequently, a lot of HTML5 apps ended up being <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/14/hybrid-inappropriateness/">wrapped in native code</a> so as to get a chance to compete in the app stores. Amazon's support of HTML5 is a much needed <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/03/04/its-a-question-of-wow/">shot-in-the-arm for HTML5</a> because it means a direct channel to mass consumers; what's more, Amazon also is offering a chance to monetize HTML5 apps <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/sdk/webapps/iap/understanding.html">via a JavaScript In-App purchase API</a>. While Amazon isn't the first In-App purchase API for HTML5, it's the first one linked to a major e-commerce platform and mass consumer channel.</p>

<p>HTML5 is by no means a silver bullet for mobile app development. There's a time and a place for HTML5 apps, just as there's still a need to create native apps. Nevertheless, HTML5 continues to gain favor as app stores (like Amazon's App store for Android) begin to distribute HTML5 apps and other platforms begin to capture market share.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[App signing: iOS versus Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/26/app-signing-ios-versus-android/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T10:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/26/app-signing-ios-versus-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/mine/sealed.jpg">Apple's app signing process can be a real pain-in-the-neck; nevertheless, it works to keep apps trusted. You know when you download a Bank of America app from iTunes that it's the real thing. You know that the app comes from <em>the</em> Bank of America.</p>

<p>On the other hand, Android allows apps to be self-signed. This has a fundamental flaw: an Android developer can claim to be anyone they want, <em>including Bank of America</em>. Thus, when you download an app from an Android App store, there's a real possibility that the app was submitted by a charlatan. What's more, those charlatan apps can actually be malicious!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://twitter.com/danieleran">Daniel Eran Dilger</a> has written an excellent article that features the differences between Apple's signing process and Google's. I highly recommend you read his article entitled "<a href="http://appleinsider.com/articles/13/07/14/editorial-googles-android-haunted-by-steve-jobs-warnings-on-app-signing-security">Google's Android haunted by Steve Jobs' warnings on app signing security</a>" as it sheds a bright light on the differences between the two mobile platforms; moreover, the article does a great job of outlining the evolution of iOS and its app security policies.</p>

<p>And while you are at it, check out my article entitled "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Sign, seal, and deliver your Android app</a>" and learn how to sign your Android app in preparation for submitting it to an app store!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mobile for the masses: Sign, seal, and deliver your Android app]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/17/mobile-for-the-masses-sign-seal-and-deliver-your-android-app/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T15:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/17/mobile-for-the-masses-sign-seal-and-deliver-your-android-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The fifth article in <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/">IBM developerWorks</a>' series <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/views/java/libraryview.jsp?search_by=mobile+for+the+masses">Mobile for the Masses</a> has been published! <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html">This hip article</a> shows you how to add a multiple-choice quiz to your Android mobile app, then sign it with a secure digital certificate.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As the article summary states:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>By web logic, content is king; but for mobile users, interaction rules. Static information design is out for mobile apps, and gamification is in. This month Andrew Glover concludes his introduction to Android mobile development by adding a multiple-choice quiz feature to the example app, Overheard Word, introduced in a previous article. Then he shows you how to generate a digital signature and publish and promote your signed app on Google Play or Amazon Appstore for Android.</p><footer><strong>IBM DeveloperWorks</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html'>Mobile for the Masses: Sign, Seal, and Deliver Your Android App</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Check out "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Sign, seal, and deliver your Android app</a>" and learn how to sign your app in preparation for submitting it to an app store! If you missed the first article, check out "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses1/">Mobile for the masses: A gentle introduction to Android</a>"; what's more, don't forget to read my second article, entitled "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses2/">Mobile for the masses: Take a swipe at it! Programming gestures in Android</a>" and the third article "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/j-mobileforthemasses3/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Activities and icons in your Android application lifecycle</a>". Finally, don't forget to read article number four: "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/j-mobileforthemasses4/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Mobile for the masses: Words and gestures with Overheard Word</a>" and programmatically integrate third-party code into your Android UI!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more articles in this series and don't forget to watch for <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/mobile/">mobile focused articles on this blog</a> as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[8% is itty-bitty, but it matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/09/8-percent-is-itty-bitty-but-it-matters/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-09T15:49:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/09/8-percent-is-itty-bitty-but-it-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I saw some news related to <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/12/02/comprehending-the-mobile-development-landscape/">Microsoft Windows Phone</a> that gave me pause for thought. Specifically, <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/ios-up-android-down-in-the-us-as-windows-phone-hits-eight-percent-in-europe-7000020117/">I read an article</a> that stated:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Microsoft's mobile platform reached new heights in the three months to July 2013 in Europe, making up 8.2 percent of sales across UK, France, Germany, Italy and Spain</p><footer><strong>Liam Tung</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.zdnet.com/ios-up-android-down-in-the-us-as-windows-phone-hits-eight-percent-in-europe-7000020117/'>iOS Up, Android Down in the US as Windows Phone Hits Eight Percent in Europe</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>While <a href="http://www.expertreviews.co.uk/smartphones/1301902/windows-phone-market-share-growing-in-europe">8.2% market share</a> might seem insignificant, what's interesting is that</p>

<p><blockquote><p>At the same time last year, Windows Phone accounted for 4.9 percent of sales</p><footer><strong>Liam Tung</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.zdnet.com/ios-up-android-down-in-the-us-as-windows-phone-hits-eight-percent-in-europe-7000020117/'>iOS Up, Android Down in the US as Windows Phone Hits Eight Percent in Europe</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>That is, <a href="http://wmpoweruser.com/kantar-windows-phone-hits-record-high-of-8-2-market-share-in-europe/">Windows Phone market share</a> for the same five markets has increased by a little more than 3% over the last year. Accordingly, Windows Phone is a <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/05/09/hold-your-horses-its-still-only-a-two-horse-race/">growing platform (in some markets)</a>, which means developers will eventually need to start considering it as a <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/05/09/hold-your-horses-its-still-only-a-two-horse-race/">third platform</a>. And throwing a third platform into the mix does change the variables in a native versus <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/05/crowd-think-often-lacks-clarity/">non-native</a> argument <em>in favor of an HTML5 approach</em>.</p>

<p>Microsoft has deep pockets and has <a href="http://www.latimes.com/business/technology/la-fi-tn-microsoft-ceo-steve-ballmers-failures-20130823,0,5988522,full.story">shown before</a> that it will fight (and hang on) to create a market for itself (i.e. Xbox and Bing). I suspect that Windows Phone will continue to gain market share, albeit slowly, mostly at the expense of nominal platforms like Blackberry.</p>

<p>Consequently, HTML5 will continue on its path as an advantageous development platform; moreover, HTML5's rise will <em>most likely be at the expense of hybrid frameworks</em> as there's a point of diminishing returns for <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/14/hybrid-inappropriateness/">frameworks</a> to support 100% of all native features across multiple native platforms. Plus, Amazon's recent announcement that their <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/07/why-amazon-appstores-support-of-html5-matters/">Appstore for Android supports the submission of HTML5 apps</a> only adds to the pro-HTML5 argument.</p>

<p>8% is an itty-bitty number, but I'll be keeping an eye on Microsoft's Windows Phone market share. And I'll be watching the world of HTML5 closely. How about you?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Amazon Appstore's support of HTML5 matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/07/why-amazon-appstores-support-of-html5-matters/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T21:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/07/why-amazon-appstores-support-of-html5-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/G/01/mobile-apps/devportal2/content/sdk/images/webapps_icon-final-114.<em>V379662584</em>.png">Today, Amazon announced that their <a href="http://www.amazon.com/mobile-apps/b?ie=UTF8&amp;node=2350149011">Appstore for Android</a> <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/post/Tx2HGWRGOW5YG8/Amazon-is-Now-Accepting-HTML5-Web-Apps-Making-it-Easy-for-You-to-Reach-Millions.html">now supports the submission of HTML5 apps</a>. This is a game changer for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML5">HTML5</a> because now there is a direct channel to consumers.</p>

<p>As I wrote almost a year ago:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>software delivery on the mobile platform is, at least for the foreseeable future, firmly established via app stores. And app stores cater to native apps (100% native and/or hybrid) only. The average person will not look for useful apps via their device’s browser: that route is still a jungle. And, at this point, there is no viable pure play mobile web app delivery channel.</p><footer><strong>thediscoblog.com</strong> <cite><a href='http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/09/07/past-performance-is-no-guarantee-of-future-results/'>Past Performance Is No Guarantee of Future Results</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Today, it's still true that the most convenient mechanism  for app delivery on mobile devices (and increasingly desktops) is via various app stores. And until today, HTML5 apps were not included in these app stores (unless they were wrapped by some hybrid-web container like <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/04/14/hybrid-inappropriateness/">PhoneGap</a>).</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But now with Amazon's announcement, <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/html5/">HTML5</a> apps <em>without any native container</em> can be submitted into their Appstore. What's more, these apps can take advantage of monetization features like <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/sdk/webapps/iap/understanding.html">In-App purchasing</a> using Amazon's API.</p>

<p>Now HTML5 apps have a direct channel to consumers along with an API to make HTML5 app developers money. HTML5 apps are now icon-ized and people don't have to use a search engine to find them!</p>

<p>As <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/blog/author/Mike+Hines.html">Mike Hines</a> of Amazon puts it:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Starting today, you can submit your web apps and mobile optimized web sites and have them merchandised alongside native apps on Amazon and Kindle Fire in nearly 200 countries worldwide, without any third-party software or doing any native app development.</p><footer><strong>https://developer.amazon.com/blog/</strong> <cite><a href='https://developer.amazon.com/post/Tx2HGWRGOW5YG8/Amazon-is-Now-Accepting-HTML5-Web-Apps-Making-it-Easy-for-You-to-Reach-Millions.html'>Amazon Is Now Accepting HTML5 Web Apps—Making It Easy for You to Reach Millions of Kindle Fire and Android Customers Worldwide</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>This is big news for HTML5 developers. A direct channel to the masses and monetization APIs to boot -- what more could you ask for? Standby folks because it's about to get even more interesting, as I'm willing to bet that Google and Apple will follow suit in the near future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
