<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Java | The Disco Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-09T19:00:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://thediscoblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Glover]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[All other metrics are useless]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/10/09/all-other-metrics-are-useless/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T18:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/10/09/all-other-metrics-are-useless</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/mine/time1.jpg">When it comes to queues, whether they're implemented as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_Message_Service">JMS</a>, database tables (i.e. what Ruby's <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/06/10/backgrounding-tasks-in-heroku-with-delayed-job/">Delayed::Job</a> uses for a queue), or even <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/sqs/">Amazon's SQS</a>, the most common metric used to evaluate the state of a queue is its length. In essence, one derives an efficiency metric based upon how many messages are residing in a queue at any given time. If there are just a few messages, the queue is operating efficiently. If there are numerous messages, things are inefficient and alarms must be sounded.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But what if you're in a consistently busy environment with extreme bursts where queues have the tendency to rapidly fill up? If you have sufficient workers <em>already running</em> to handle that burst, do you need to fire up more?</p>

<p>You can fire up more workers, but doing so might cost you. That is, you might have to provision new worker instances, such as <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/dynos">Heroku worker dynos</a> or AWS AMIs, which will end up costing you tangible money. And sometimes those worker instances take a few moments to fire up and when they're operational, the burst of activity is over and the queue is back to normal -- the initially available workers handled the load adequately.</p>

<p>It turns out that the queue's length was a lagging indicator. You spun up unneeded resources. False alarm!</p>

<p>If you already have sufficient capacity to handle the influx of messages on a queue, then monitoring a queue's length isn't too helpful. In fact, it's a misleading metric and can cause you to take unneeded actions.</p>

<p>Consequently, a queue's length <em>is not indicative of a system's efficiency</em> when there's already sufficient workers present. Rather, the metric that means something in a high capacity environment is <em>how long a message resides in a queue</em>. That is an actionable metric: if messages are stuck in a queue waiting to be processed then you need more processors!</p>

<h2>Moo over queue length and let queue wait time in</h2>

<p>By default, <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-javadev2-17/">Amazon's SQS</a> doesn't provide the ability to query how long a message has been residing in a queue. Therefore, <a href="https://github.com/aglover/moo">I wrote Moo</a>.</p>

<p>Moo provides an interface for clients to obtain and take action on the message time in queue metric. This is done by augmenting an SQS message with a time stamp. That time stamp is then checked when a message is popped off of an SQS queue. If a threshold difference is exceed, then a callback is invoked.</p>

<p>Users of Moo will find its usage similar to <a href="https://github.com/aglover/ahoy">Ahoy!</a>, which is an asynchronous callback oriented facade on top of <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/sdkforjava/">AWS's Java SDK</a>. In fact, Moo uses Ahoy! underneath, with the added feature of attaching a "maximum time in queue" asynchronous callback.</p>

<p>Moo supports multiple time in queue thresholds and setting a maximum time in queue threshold is done like so:</p>

<p>``` java Adding a maximum threshold for time in queue
//adds a 1 second max threshold
sqs.addQueueWaitTimeCallback(1000, new QueueWaitTimeCallback() {
  public void onThresholdExceeded(long waitTime) {</p>

<pre><code>//waitTime is the actual time in queue
//do something... like fire off a web hook, etc
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>Note the <code>addQueueWaitTimeCallback</code> method takes a millisecond maximum time in queue value and an accompanying <code>QueueWaitTimeCallback</code> callback implementation. The <code>onThresholdExceeded</code> method will be invoked asynchronously during a message receive if the maximum threshold value is exceeded; what's more, the <code>onThresholdExceeded</code> will receive as a parameter the actual queue wait time.</p>

<h4>Show me the Moo</h4>

<p>To fire up an instance of Moo, you have a number of options, including configuring an instance of AWS's <code>AmazonSQS</code> or just passing along a key, secret, and queue name like so:</p>

<p><code>
SQS sqs = new SQS(System.getProperty("key"), System.getProperty("secret"), System.getProperty("queue"));
</code></p>

<p>Next, you can attach zero to many <code>QueueWaitTimeCallback</code> instances like so:</p>

<p>```
sqs.addQueueWaitTimeCallback(600000, new QueueWaitTimeCallback() {
  public void onThresholdExceeded(long actualWaitTime) {</p>

<pre><code>//do something -- fire off SNS message?
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>In this case, I've added a callback to be invoked if messages are in a queue longer than 10 minutes. Note, these <code>QueueWaitTimeCallback</code> callbacks are fired by the <em>queue reader</em> instance; accordingly, a <code>QueueWaitTimeCallback</code> can certainly fire up more instances of itself, for example.</p>

<p>Here's a sample JSON document that you might want to throw onto an SQS queue:</p>

<p>```
{ "employees":[</p>

<pre><code>  { "firstName":"John", "lastName":"Doe" },
  { "firstName":"Anna", "lastName":"Smith" },
  { "firstName":"Peter", "lastName":"Jones" }
</code></pre>

<p>]}
```</p>

<p>Sending and receiving this message are exactly like you'd do if you were using Ahoy!. For example, to send a message, just pass along a <code>String</code> to the <code>send</code> method:</p>

<p>```
sqs.send(json, new SendCallback() {
  public void onSend(String messageId) {</p>

<pre><code>//messageId is from SQS
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>Note, the <code>send</code> method takes an optional <code>SendCallback</code>.</p>

<p>Receiving a message is via the <code>receive</code> method, which takes a mandatory <code>ReceiveCallback</code> -- this callback will be invoked asynchronously <em>for each</em> message received off of a queue. Each instance will receive the message placed upon the queue and the message's SQS id.</p>

<p>```
sqs.receive(new ReceiveCallback() {
  public void onReceive(String messageId, String message) {</p>

<pre><code>//do something w/the message -- in this case it's JSON
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>Note, if upon the receive of a message, Moo notices that a message has been waiting in a queue for more than the max queue wait time threshold configured for an associated <code>QueueWaitTimeCallback</code>, Moo will invoke it. Note, Moo can invoke more than one instance; thus, you can set up a chain to take various actions as times increase.</p>

<p>Remember, a queue's length is usually a lagging indicator.  The metric that actually means something is how long a message resides in a queue. That's an actionable metric and <a href="https://github.com/aglover/moo">Moo</a> gives you the ability to do something about it! Can you dig it?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ahoy there callbacks!]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/29/ahoy-there-callbacks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-29T16:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/29/ahoy-there-callbacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/callback.jpg">Because it's my bag, I like <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/javascript/">JavaScript</a>. In fact, I've grown to love JavaScritp's asynchronous <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Callback_(computer_programming">callback oriented style of programming</a>. Consequently, when I find myself in a non-JavaScript environment, say, like <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/java/">Java</a>, I tend to miss using callbacks.</p>

<p>The good news is that you can <em>emulate</em> asynchronous callbacks in Java. In fact, I did just that recently with a library I've dubbed <a href="https://github.com/aglover/ahoy">Ahoy!</a>, which is an asynchronous <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-javadev2-17/">SQS adapter</a> for AWS's Java <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/sqs/">SQS</a> library.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For the uninitiated, <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-javadev2-17/">SQS is a cloud based messaging platform</a> -- with SQS you can create queues and put messages onto those queues, which can then be read -- later or immediately by some other process or the same exact process. All of this leverages Amazon’s massively redundant architecture to offer extremely high availability in the face of concurrent access.</p>

<p>Asynchronous callbacks in Java can be achieved with two features: anonymous classes (containing one method) and Java's <code>java.util.concurrent</code> package.</p>

<p>Because Java doesn't allow you to pass functions (or methods) <em>easily</em> as a parameter, to simulate a callback, you can create an interface that contains one method, which basically mimics a function. In the case of Ahoy, there are two interfaces: <code>MessageSendCallback</code> and <code>MessageReceivedCallback</code> -- both have one method: <code>onSend</code> and <code>onReceive</code> respectively. Accordingly, Ahoy!''s primary class, dubbed <code>SQSAdapter</code> exposes two simple methods: <code>send</code> and <code>receive</code> and both take their related callback interface.</p>

<p>The most straightforward callback to understand is the <code>receive</code> method. As you can imagine, <code>receive</code> is intended to handle behavior when a message is received off of a particular queue. Thus, the <code>receive</code> method is defined as follows:</p>

<p><code>java SQSAdapter's receive method
public void receive(final MessageReceivedCallback callback) {}
</code></p>

<p>The <code>MessageReceivedCallback</code> interface looks like this:</p>

<p>``` java The MessageReceivedCallback interface
public interface MessageReceivedCallback {</p>

<pre><code>public void onReceive(String messageId, String message);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Note, the <code>onReceive</code> method takes a message id (which is particular to SQS) and the message itself -- which in the case of SQS is always a <code>String</code> (that <code>String</code> can hold anything you want, keep in mind: JSON, XML, byte sequence, etc).</p>

<p>Thus, clients of Ahoy! provide the intended behavior for a message when it is received. This behavior could be to write something to a database, generate another message and send it on another queue, you name it.</p>

<p>Now the interesting part is the implementation of Ahoy!'s <code>receive</code> method. To achieve asynchronocity, I employed Java's <code>java.util.concurrent</code> package, which sadly, seems to be under appreciated.</p>

<p>``` java The receive method's implementation with callback being invoked
private void receive(final AmazonSQS sqs, final String queueURL, final MessageReceivedCallback callback) {
  pool.execute(new Runnable() {</p>

<pre><code>public void run() {
  final List&lt;Message&gt; messages = sqs.receiveMessage(
          new ReceiveMessageRequest(queueURL).withMaxNumberOfMessages(10).withWaitTimeSeconds(20)).getMessages();
  if (messages.size() &gt; 0) {
      for (final Message message : messages) {
        callback.onReceive(message.getMessageId(), message.getBody());
        sqs.deleteMessage(new DeleteMessageRequest(queueURL, message.getReceiptHandle()));
      }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  });
}
```</p>

<p>With a fixed Thread pool, a thread is created, which waits for messages to arrive on a particular queue; when one shows up, the passed in <code>MessageReceivedCalledback</code> is invoked for each message.</p>

<p>For an example of how this works for clients of Ahoy!, here's a test case that verifies the execution of the callback:</p>

<p>``` java The receive method implemented
final boolean[] wasReceived = {false};
ahoy.receive(new MessageReceivedCallback() {
  public void onReceive(String messageId, String message) {</p>

<pre><code>wasReceived[0] = true;
assertNotNull("message id was null", messageId);
assertEquals("message wasn't " + origMessage, origMessage, message);
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>Likewise, sending a message is similar -- a new <code>Runnable</code> instance is created, which sends a particular message and invokes the passed in <code>MessageSentCallback</code>'s <code>onSend</code> method, passing in the newly sent messages's id.</p>

<p>``` java The send method is also asynchronous
private void send(final AmazonSQS sqs, final String queueURL, final String message, final MessageSentCallback callback) {
  pool.execute(new Runnable() {</p>

<pre><code>  public void run() {
  SendMessageResult res = sqs.sendMessage(new SendMessageRequest(queueURL, message));
  if (callback != null) {
    callback.onSend(res.getMessageId());
  }
  }
</code></pre>

<p>  });
}
```</p>

<p>Incidentally, the AWS Java SDK <em>does provide an asynchronous client</em>; however, this client's implementation leverages Java's <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/Future.html">Futures</a>. While <a href="http://nurkiewicz.blogspot.com/2013/02/javautilconcurrentfuture-basics.html">Futures are a neat concept</a>, Ahoy!'s implementation is more convenient (<em>at least for me and in the patterns of how I employ SQS</em>) than Futures as there isn't any polling involved once a message is sent or received.</p>

<p>While callbacks aren't <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Function_object#In_Java">necessarily supported</a> natively in Java, you can emulate them quite nicely and achieve the same level of code conciseness as what's common in JavaScript. And if you need a handy way to interface with AWS SQS, <a href="https://github.com/aglover/ahoy">then give Ahoy! a try</a>! Can you dig it, man?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mobile for the masses: Sign, seal, and deliver your Android app]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/17/mobile-for-the-masses-sign-seal-and-deliver-your-android-app/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T15:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/09/17/mobile-for-the-masses-sign-seal-and-deliver-your-android-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The fifth article in <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/">IBM developerWorks</a>' series <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/views/java/libraryview.jsp?search_by=mobile+for+the+masses">Mobile for the Masses</a> has been published! <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html">This hip article</a> shows you how to add a multiple-choice quiz to your Android mobile app, then sign it with a secure digital certificate.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As the article summary states:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>By web logic, content is king; but for mobile users, interaction rules. Static information design is out for mobile apps, and gamification is in. This month Andrew Glover concludes his introduction to Android mobile development by adding a multiple-choice quiz feature to the example app, Overheard Word, introduced in a previous article. Then he shows you how to generate a digital signature and publish and promote your signed app on Google Play or Amazon Appstore for Android.</p><footer><strong>IBM DeveloperWorks</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html'>Mobile for the Masses: Sign, Seal, and Deliver Your Android App</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Check out "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/mo-mobileforthemasses5/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Sign, seal, and deliver your Android app</a>" and learn how to sign your app in preparation for submitting it to an app store! If you missed the first article, check out "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses1/">Mobile for the masses: A gentle introduction to Android</a>"; what's more, don't forget to read my second article, entitled "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-mobileforthemasses2/">Mobile for the masses: Take a swipe at it! Programming gestures in Android</a>" and the third article "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/j-mobileforthemasses3/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Activities and icons in your Android application lifecycle</a>". Finally, don't forget to read article number four: "<a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/j-mobileforthemasses4/index.html">Mobile for the masses: Mobile for the masses: Words and gestures with Overheard Word</a>" and programmatically integrate third-party code into your Android UI!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more articles in this series and don't forget to watch for <a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/mobile/">mobile focused articles on this blog</a> as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes TDD requires a hammer]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/04/sometimes-tdd-requires-a-hammer/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-04T11:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/04/sometimes-tdd-requires-a-hammer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/mine/hammerj.jpg">While there are myriad mocking libraries available for the Java platform, only a select few of these nifty frameworks is capable of mocking the non-mock-friendly modifiers of <code>static</code> and <code>final</code>. Static (or class) methods, while handy for factories, become a nuisance for a framework like <a href="https://code.google.com/p/mockito/">Mockito</a>, however, with the inclusion of <a href="https://code.google.com/p/powermock/">PowerMock</a>, you've got yourself a proverbial hammer.</p>

<p><a href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/01/imbibing-the-fluency-of-mockito/">As I wrote about previously</a>, I had to deal with a 3rd party library that is used to integrate with a networked service. This library is essentially hardwired to interact with homebase, which naturally provides some challenges when trying to test ones code that relies on this library. Moreover, the said library contained a <code>static</code> method for creating instances of a specialized class, which, naturally, my code depended on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>PowerMock is made to work in concert with either <a href="http://easymock.org/">EasyMock</a> or <a href="https://code.google.com/p/powermock/wiki/MockitoUsage13">Mockito</a>; what's more, it comes with a custom runner for inclusion in <a href="https://github.com/junit-team/junit">JUnit</a>. I'm going to show you how to use PowerMock with Mockito as I happen to find Mockito's syntax much more fluent than EasyMock's.</p>

<p>For starters, you'll need to use two class level annotations -- <code>@RunWith</code> for specifying the <code>PowerMockRunner</code> class (this is a JUnit annotation) and another dubbed <code>@PrepareForTest</code>, which takes the class with <code>static</code> methods you wish to mock. <code>@PrepareForTest</code> is provided by PowerMock.</p>

<p>In my case, the class containing a <code>static</code> method is named <code>QTP</code>, accordingly; my test class looks like this:</p>

<p><code>java JUnit test class with class level annotations
@RunWith(PowerMockRunner.class)
@PrepareForTest(QTP.class)
public class CreateCommandTest {
  @Test
  public void testCreateRequest() throws Exception {}
}
</code></p>

<p>Next, in your test method, you use <code>PowerMokito</code>'s <code>mockStatic</code> method, which takes the class (again) with static methods you wish to mock.</p>

<p><code>java JUnit test case using PowerMock &amp; Mockito
@Test
public void testCreateRequest() throws Exception {
  PowerMockito.mockStatic(QTP.class);
  //....
}
</code></p>

<p>You can then mock a static method on the class you've been passing around to <code>mockStatic</code> and the <code>@PrepareForTest</code> annotation like you would normally do with Mockito. For instance, I can use the <code>when</code> method to specify what I want to happen when this static method is invoked.</p>

<p><code>java Using normal Mockito actions for mocking
@Test
public void testCreateRequest() throws Exception {
  PowerMockito.mockStatic(QTP.class);
  QTP qtpThing = mock(QTP.class); //normal Mockito mocking
  //QTP.create is static
  when(QTP.create("dm2q", "0C4F7501UDC8C1EB43B06C988")).thenReturn(qtpThing);
  //QTP.createRecord isn't static
  when(qtpThing.createRecord(any(Tckt.class))).thenReturn(new Long(1000000L));
  //...
}
</code></p>

<p>Finally, you can use <a href="http://metlos.wordpress.com/2012/09/14/the-dark-powers-of-powermock/">PowerMock</a> to ensure your mocked static method is actually invoked. The requirements here are a bit funky; that is, it requires you <em>first</em> specify how many times with one line of code and then you <em>actually call the static method</em>.</p>

<p><code>java Verifying your mocked static method was invoked
@Test
public void testCreateRequest() throws Exception {  
  //...
  PowerMockito.verifyStatic(Mockito.times(1));
  QTP.create("dm2q", "0C4F7501UDC8C1EB43B06C988");
  //...
}
</code></p>

<p>Yeah, that's sorta confusing, I know.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, as most people in the world of Java figured out long ago, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2671496/java-when-to-use-static-methods">static methods</a> are <a href="http://misko.hevery.com/2008/12/15/static-methods-are-death-to-testability/">somewhat difficult</a> when it <a href="http://blog.codecentric.de/en/2011/11/testing-and-mocking-of-static-methods-in-java/">comes to testing</a>. That is, while a method that conceptually has no state, at first glance, seems straightforward enough to test, the <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2472690/in-java-is-there-any-disadvantage-to-static-methods-on-a-class">issues arise</a> when that static method does something like hit a database or in my case, call a web service to a networked asset. There is no easy way to override such behavior (unless, of course, you pull out a hammer).</p>

<p>Static methods have a place. But when it comes to testing code, whether it be legacy or some 3rd party library, the <code>static</code> modifier requires a hammer and as I hope I've shown you, <a href="https://code.google.com/p/powermock/">PowerMock</a> is that hammer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Imbibing the fluency of Mockito]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/01/imbibing-the-fluency-of-mockito/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-01T15:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/08/01/imbibing-the-fluency-of-mockito</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/Mockito.jpg">I recently found myself writing some code to integrate two disparate platforms. One of these systems is Java based and the other, while not written in Java, offers a Java API. I'll call these systems Foo and Bar, respectively.</p>

<p>It became obvious before I had written a line of code, however, that testing the eventual adapter would require I explicitly mock the later system's API (i.e. Foo's) as all I had to go with was a jar file whose classes and methods made it clear they communicated with a live instance.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>I spent a few cycles to see what's new in the world of Java mocking and I was pleased to see that my old friend <a href="https://code.google.com/p/mockito/">Mockito</a> is still active and is indeed, still an <a href="http://www.javaworld.com/community/node/3772">excellent tool</a> for general purpose mocking. For the uninitiated, <a href="http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/mockito">Mockito</a> is Java based mocking framework that:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>...tastes really good. It lets you write beautiful tests with [a] clean &amp; simple API. Mockito doesn't give you hangover because the tests are very readable and they produce clean verification errors.</p><footer><strong>Google code mockito project page</strong> <cite><a href='https://code.google.com/p/mockito/'>Why Drink It?</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Indeed, Mockito offers a <a href="https://code.google.com/p/easyb/wiki/UsingMockito">simple, fluent API</a> that allows you to precisely mock behaviors without a lot of fuss. For instance, the main facade to interface with Bar is via a <code>QTP</code> class that has methods like <code>logIn</code>, <code>logOut</code>, etc. Rather than relying on classes under test to actually invoke these methods, I can easily create mock instances of <code>QTP</code> with Mockito like so:</p>

<p><code>java Mocking an instance of QTP
QTP qtpThing = mock(QTP.class);
</code></p>

<p>Where <code>mock</code> is a statically imported method from <code>org.mockito.Mockito</code>. With a mock instance, I can then dictate how I wish certain methods to behave, <em>provided I pass along this mocked instance to my classes under test</em>.</p>

<p>For example, the method <code>logIn</code> doesn't return anything; in fact, one must invoke that method first and then call another method to generate a ticket (or token), which will be used on subsequent method invocations. Thus, the adapter that I'm writing will receive some input values (from Foo in the form of XML) and the adapter will return a ticket (in the form of an XML document as per Foo's required XML schema).</p>

<p>Accordingly, the test this interaction, I need to do two things:</p>

<ul>
<li>ensure that the <code>logIn</code> method was invoked with specific parameters</li>
<li>mock the response of a valid ticket, via the <code>getTicket</code> method</li>
</ul>


<p>What's more, I'd also like to verify that a <code>logIn</code> failure results in a particular interaction from within my adapter code. Therefore, I'll need to mock out some exceptional behavior as well.</p>

<p>In the case of mocking out a particular method, you simply chain together a few methods; in my case, <code>when</code> and <code>thenReturn</code> do the trick like so:</p>

<p><code>java Mocking the behavior of getTicket
when(qtpThing.getTicket()).thenReturn("test-ticket");
</code></p>

<p>In the code above, when the <code>getTicket</code> method is invoked on my mock instance, the <code>String</code> "test-ticket" will be returned.</p>

<p>Next, to ensure that <code>logIn</code> was invoked with parameters obtained from an incoming XML document, I can use Mockito's <code>verify</code> method.</p>

<p><code>java Using Mockito's verify to ensure proper interaction
verify(qtpThing, times(1)).logIn("some_value", "some_user_name", "password");
</code></p>

<p>In this case, the <code>verify</code> method checks that <code>logIn</code> is invoked one time and that three particular <code>String</code> values are passed in. If these expectations are not met, Mockito will throw an exception (and your corresponding test case will fail).</p>

<p>Thus, my test case for verifying my adapter is quite simple, yet highly readable.</p>

<p><code>java JUnit test case for verifying logIn behavior
@Test
public void testLoginRequest() throws Exception {
  QTP qtpThing = mock(QTP.class);
  when(qtpThing.getTicket()).thenReturn("test-ticket");
  AdapterRequest request = new AdapterRequest(XML.read("etc/test-login-req.xml"));
  QbosAdapter adapter = new QbosAdapter();
  adapter.setQtpInstance(qtpThing);
  AdapterResponse adapterResponse = adapter.performAction(request);
  assertNotNull(adapterResponse);
  verify(qtpThing, times(1)).logIn("some_value", "some_user_name", "password");
  assertEquals("test-ticket", adapterResponse.getData().getText());
}
</code></p>

<p>What if I need to simulate an exception thrown by the <code>QTP</code> object, ostensibly from an invalid parameter or incorrect credentials during a log in? Again, Mockito's fluent API makes this a breeze.</p>

<p>In my case, I'd like the <code>logIn</code> method to throw one of the checked methods in its method signature named <code>UnknownQtpException</code>. You can do this via the <code>doThrow</code> and <code>when</code> methods.</p>

<p><code>java Mocking out exceptions in Mockito
doThrow(new UnknownQtpException()).when(qtpThing).logIn("", "blah", "blah");
</code></p>

<p>In the code above, I'm explicitly declaring that if the first parameter to the <code>logIn</code> command is blank, then my mocked <code>QTP</code> instance should throw <code>UnknownQtpException</code>. Putting everything together yields the following test case:</p>

<p><code>java Testing exceptional circumstances with JUnit &amp; Mockito
@Test
public void testFailureLoginRequest() throws Exception {
  QTP qtpThing = mock(QTP.class);
  doThrow(new UnknownQtpException()).when(qtpThing).logIn("", "blah", "blah");
  XML xml = XML.read("etc/test-login-req-err.xml");
  AdapterRequest request = new AdapterRequest(xml);
  QbosAdapter adapter = new QbosAdapter();
  adapter.setQtpInstance(qtpThing);
  AdapterResponse adapterResponse = adapter.performAction(request);
  assertNotNull(adapterResponse);
  verify(qtpThing, times(1)).logIn("", "blah", "blah");
  assertEquals("FAILURE", adapterResponse.getData().getText());
}
</code></p>

<p>The beauty, of course, is that my test cases effectively test my adapter code without relying on a third party system (in this case, Bar). This is naturally a time honored testing technique employable in any language with a mocking framework worth its salt!</p>

<p>If you find yourself writing some integration code in Java, then I can't recommend Mockito enough. <a href="http://www.javaworld.com/community/node/3772">Mockito's API</a> is quite straightforward and it makes tests easy to comprehend. I mean, it makes tests easy to imbibe.  Dig it?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
