<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cloud | The Disco Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/categories/cloud/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-26T11:29:07-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://thediscoblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Glover]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AWS EBS in 4 steps]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/10/12/aws-ebs-in-4-steps/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T17:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2013/10/12/aws-ebs-in-4-steps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/mine/4fingers.jpg">When you fire up an AWS AMI, you are given a small partition of disk space that survives reboots. For example, the base <a href="https://github.com/aglover/ubuntu-equip">Ubuntu AMI</a> I tend to favor comes with an 8GB primary partition; however, 8GB is often not enough, especially if you're running a database or something that requires a lot of disk space.</p>

<p>If you poke around on an AMI instance, you'll notice some AMI instances will have additional partitions and in many cases, these partitions will be huge; nevertheless, they're transient and any data on those disks will disappear after a reboot.</p>

<p>Accordingly, if you need to gain some more permanent space on an AMI instance, you'll need to leverage an <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ebs/">Elastic Block Store (or EBS)</a>, which is basically a permanent hard disk that you can attach to a running AMI instance. The data on an EBS will survive a reboot.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Attaching an <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/articles/1667">EBS is super simple</a> and can be done in 4 steps. These steps assume you've got a running AMI; accordingly, if you don't have one up and running, go ahead and do that first. Finally, these instructions are for Linix/Unix systems.</p>

<p>First, you'll need to create an EBS volume in the same zone as the AMI instance. In my case, the instance I'd like to augment with a beefy hard drive resides in us-east-1b. What's more, you'll need to configure how much space you'll want -- you can also select if you'd like to have <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2012/07/31/announcing-provisioned-iops-for-amazon-ebs/">provisioned IOPS</a> -- this is a high performance I/O feature of AWS and is intended for databases.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/mine/ebs1.png"></p>

<p>Once the EBS is created, you'll need to <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSEC2/latest/UserGuide/ebs-attaching-volume.html">attach it</a> to your running AMI -- you can do this by right clicking on the EBS in the AWS Management Console and selecting Attach Volume. You'll need to pick your instance from a drop down. Once you've picked your instance, AWS will suggest a Device -- I suggest you keep it. Click the "Yes, Attach" button.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/mine/ebs2.png"></p>

<p>SSH onto your running instance and take a peek at the <code>/proc/partitions</code> file -- you should see at least 2 partitions with your newly attached one on the bottom.  The blocks are listed in kilobytes and pay special attention to the name -- you'll need it for the next few steps.</p>

<p>``` bash The contents of /proc/partitions
ubuntu@ip-10-194-97-73:~$ cat /proc/partitions
major minor  #blocks  name</p>

<p> 202        1    8388608 xvda1
 202       80    8388608 xvdf
```</p>

<p>As you can see above, there is an 8GB EBS volume named <code>xvdf</code> in the <code>partitions</code> file.</p>

<p>Next, you'll want to format the volume -- I'm going to format the EBS volume as ext4. The command to do this is:</p>

<p><code>bash Foratting an EBS volume
sudo mke2fs -F -t ext4 /dev/xvdf
</code></p>

<p>Now that the volume is formatted, I can mount it -- I'm going to mount it to a directory called <code>/ebs</code>; accordingly, I need to create the <code>/ebs</code> directory and then mount the <code>xvdf</code> device like so:</p>

<p><code>bash Creating and mounting the device to the ebs directory
sudo mkdir /ebs
sudo mount /dev/xvdf /ebs
</code></p>

<p>At this point, you are 98% done; however, the volume will not be reattached if this instance is rebooted.</p>

<p>To make this EBS volume automatically reattach after a reboot, you'll need to add it to the <code>fstab</code> file (it's in the <code>/etc</code> directory). When you edit that file, the file system will be
what ever you mounted (i.e <code>/dev/xvdf</code>), the mount point will be the directory you mounted it to -- in my case, it's <code>/ebs</code>. The type will be ext4 (if you formatted it that way) and for options, put default. The last two values can be 0 as well.</p>

<p>If you need to remove your EBS volume, on the attached instance, run</p>

<p><code>bash Unmounting a device
sudo umount -d /dev/xvdf
</code></p>

<p>And then go into the AWS Management Console, find your EBS volume, right click on it and select detach volume.</p>

<p>That's it -- you're done! You've got a permanent store. In 4 steps, you've created an EBS volume, attached it to a running AMI, formatted and mounted it. And you've made it attach automatically after a reboot.  Can you dig it?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The cloud files are out!]]></title>
    <link href="http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/12/12/the-cloud-files-are-out/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://thediscoblog.com/blog/2012/12/12/the-cloud-files-are-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/t-j-f-cloudpodcast_ffffff.jpg">The good folks over at <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/">IBM developerWorks</a> have recently published <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-gloverpodcast5/index.html">season 5 of the Java technical podcast series</a>. This season
focuses on the technologies, companies, and people influencing cloud computing. I had the pleasure to chat with a cadre of super interesting people, including <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-gloverpodcast5/index.html#labourey">Sacha Labourey</a> of CloudBees, <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-gloverpodcast5/index.html#engineyard">Bill Platt and Mark Gaydos</a> of Engine Yard, and <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-gloverpodcast5/index.html#proudman">Jesse Proudman</a> of BlueBox, just to name a few!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-gloverpodcast5/index.html">In these podcasts</a>, you'll hear from people who not only influence, but directly impact cloud computing, regardless of the underlying language or platform. There's a lot to learn here, so put on your headphones and get ready for some interesting conversations! So what are you waiting for? <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-gloverpodcast5/index.html">Go listen right this instant</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
